Okay בוקר טוב *boker tov*. Today's דף *daf* is פ *peh*, 80.
We stopped at the first line at the top of the דף
*daf*. We're dealing with cases of the previous משנה mishna. *Mishnah* about
somebody who arranged to, well actually one משנה mishna. *Mishnah* but somebody
who arranged, you know, to work, to take a donkey in a
certain place and took it in another place and there was a
degree of negligence and they're liable for what comes next, right? And
then the other issue at the end of that משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*
was under what circumstances if something happens to the donkey, which is
not the fault of the renter, does the owner have to replace
it? So now we get onto similar questions about changing things in
liability, but it's not actually about the donkey, it's about certain equipment
that comes with the animal. So let's take a look. השוכר את
הפרה לחרוש בהר וחרש בבקעה *Hasocher es haparah lachrosh bahar vecharesh babikah*.
You rented the cow to plow in the mountain and you plowed
in the valley. So in the valley is presumably an easier place
to plow. So אם נשבר הקנקן *im nishbar hakamkan*, if the קנקן
*kankan* which רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says it means a sort of like
the peg that is used at the back of the plow to
make the furrow, okay, so apparently what would happen the way רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* explains it is that one person would lead the cow
and the other person would hold the peg in the back and
hold it like firm and then the pulling of the cow would
cause a furrow. And both of these people, the person driving the
cattle or whatever and the person in the backseat, would both be
rented out by the owner of the cow. So you are renting
from me, you know, it's like when, you know, well this is
not a good משל *mashal*, but you know, you rent from a
guy the U-Haul, I think actually when you rent the U-Haul you
have to pay extra for the equipment you want to come with
it. Anyway, but you rent from me a cow and I rent
with you the equipment and the workers and the whole thing. It's
a whole package deal to you. Okay,
so you're exempt in that case because because you actually made the
job easier than what's expected. ובבקעה וחרש בהר *Ubivikah vecharesh bahar*, if
however you said to do it in the valley and you did
it in the mountain and the mountain is more stony and there's
more you know it's more dangerous for the equipment, so אם נשבר
הקנקן חייב chayav *im nishbar hakamkan chayav*, then if that peg breaks
you're liable. לדוש בקטנית ודש בתבואה *Ladush bekitnis vedash betvuah*, let's say
I hired the cow to thresh, you know, to like walk on
the on the grain in order to break the kernels from the
from the husks, okay, and I did it with I did it
in order to do it for legumes and I did it for
grain, פטור patur. *patur*, then I'm exempt because presumably it's easier to
crush the grain than it is to crush the legumes. Okay, oh
and then oh yeah thank you that's not clear. It says on
the end we see that the cow slipped. So here we're back
to the issue that something happened to the cow. לדוש בתבואה ודש
בקטנית *Ladush betvuah vedash bekitnis*, so it's actually not a question of
hard or not hard, it's how slippery it is. Right. To do
it on grain and I did it on legumes, חייב chayav *chayav*,
I'm חייב chayav *chayav* משום דקטנית מחלקת *mishum dekitnis mechalkos* because legumes
are slippery. All right. So doesn't seem to be anything what? They're
softer. They're softer. So doesn't seem to be anything so new from
what we've seen before. Let's see the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. משנה Mishna
*Mishnah* says like this: היכא דלא שני מאן משלם *Heich dulo shani
baman meshalem*. Let's say you didn't do anything different, you did it
according to the you know to what the terms they arranged were,
and this peg still broke. Who pays? Now remember by the way
I the renter have not done anything. I rented it, you gave
me your cow with your two workers here, okay ראובן ושמעון *Reuven
and Shimon*, and they were plowing and it broke. So you know
so there I didn't do anything wrong. We did the arrangement, it
broke, so you know should say okay so I don't pay end
story. No, here the story is. The owner wants to get compensated
by the workers. He says to his workers, you guys were irresponsible,
you weren't careful enough, you broke it, okay? You could have been...
so therefore in the way רש"י *Rashi* explains it is although again
I don't know if this is why we assume this is necessarily
the case, that the driver must have taken it a little bit
off course. If it was going totally straight it wouldn't have broken.
At the same time the guy with the peg if he was
paying attention then even when the thing moved off course he could
have been more careful but by not paying attention once it moved
off course and he was like you know didn't sort of adjust
that caused it to break. Okay, so it's a good question, right?
You turned too quickly. You didn't adjust. You know, who's like the
both sort of you know that's why it's always hard to have
a co-pilot or whatever, right? Says cause you know one guy pulling
this way and one guy's pulling that way, you know, so who's
to blame in that case?
But what if the case is that the workers were responsible?
Right, I mean there could be a case where they're both an
אונס *ones*, but here the assumption is is that some of them
is at and we'll get to a case like that in a
minute. Okay, but here the case is that definitely there was like
shared negligence essentially. Okay, and I say you know it wouldn't have
broken if you hadn't gone off the way. Well it wouldn't have
broken if you'd been adjusted properly. So who gets who pays?
What if they actually know what if everyone did everything right and
it just broke?
Right, so we'll see I say we'll see that. So גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says okay so אמר רב פפא דמאן דפשע משלם *Amar Rapa
deman deparsha meshalem*. The one who רש"י *Rashi* says that sort of
means the you know yoke in the in the head, the one
who's leading the animal pays. He was the one that sort of
started the problem. He went off he went off the path. רב
ששת בריה
דרב אידי אמר דנקיט מנא משלם. denakit mana meshalem. No, the guy
who holds the peg in the back pays because he was the
one, I mean, that's where the, that's what broke, and maybe he
was the one that was at the, you know, last moment to
have saved it.
Okay, so והלכתא ve-hilchata the הלכה halacha is דנקיט מנא משלם. Okay,
now the guy who holds the peg. Now again, it doesn't say
why that's the הלכה, halacha, you know, does that mean that in
some way there's more negligence? Like your one way to measure negligence
is what should you have anticipated and how sloppy were you being
by not sort of seeing what was happening, right? So are we
sort of saying that this guy was sloppier than the guy up
front or are we basically saying no, they both have the shared
thing but like as it were this was the last guy in
the chain, like he was in the position that he could have
stopped it at the end? So they were both negligent but this
was the most proximate negligence that caused it.
A גרמא grama kind of thing you're going for.
Well, it's not גרמא, grama, they're handling somebody's thing and they're breaking
it.
No, but but in other words the guy not the person who's
holding the peg but the person who's...
yeah, it's an interesting question. Is it גרמא? grama? It's a little
bit like it's a little like כוחו kocho or כוח כוחו המעורב
בו, koach kocho ha-meurav bo, but you're right, there's a degree of
גרמא. grama. But the other question is, are they חייב chayav as
מזיק mazik or they חייב chayav. as שומרים? shomrim? They're sent with
the owner's stuff which the גמרא Gemara doesn't explore, which you're right,
is an important question. The assumption sounds like it's מזיק. mazik. So
why the guy leading it is considered a מזיק? mazik? Well, maybe
that's part of why the guy in the back pays. But anyway,
I also think it is a question about like proximate negligence, right?
So that's an interesting point. Like, you know, I'm trying to whatever,
I mean I could think of I can imagine other cases like
that where the question is the person most proximate who was the
last chain of the event who could have stopped it from happening,
right, that's the negligent that most directly caused it.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, והלכתא דנקיט מנא
משלם, ve-hilchata denakit mana meshalem, the guy who's holding the peg. Now
תוספות Tosafot has an interesting question. תוספות Tosafot says, I don't get
it, says תוספות, Tosafot, what about let's תוספות Tosafot says, look at
תוספות, Tosafot, וצריך לעיון אמאי לא משלם, ve-tzarich le-iyun amai lo meshalem,
ואי נמי היכא דשני נמי אמאי לא משלם אחד מן הפועלים שפשע
בשבירת הקנקן דטיבעא נמי אמשלם. ve-i nami heicha de-shinei nami amai lo
meshalem echad min ha-poalim she-pasha bishvirat ha-kankan de-tiv'a nami ameshalem.
Let's say I, the renter, did something wrong. I was negligent, I
took it on the mountain, okay, which is rockier. But nevertheless, if
you're being really careful, you can stop it you can make sure
it doesn't break on the mountain.
Meaning you just won't go or...
no, no, you're the worker. No, just be more careful. Don't push
it in as hard, look out for the rocks, be more careful.
Okay? So even if I'm negligent, right, you guys are the more
proximate negligence. So why and you guys are the ones handling it,
right? So why even if I started being negligent, why aren't you
all why don't we still ask that one of you guys who
are the workers should pay? It's a good question. Well, yeah, but
there are other people here that are responsible. That's the point. So
we have three different people we can point to. Why do we
דווקא davka point to the guy who did the first שינוי? shinui?
If actually the conclusion of the גמרא Gemara. is that the guy
with the most proximate negligence.
Okay, so the renter is breaking his contract...
well, that's what Mike was saying, so maybe he's taking responsibility. Right,
so maybe according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says כל המעביר
על דעת בעל הבית נקרא גזלן, kol ha-ma'avir al da'at ba'al ha-bayit
nikra gazlan, breaking a contract, that's one thing. But if you don't
say רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, and you say it's a question of
negligence, everybody was negligent, right? So one guy was negligent first and
they were negligent afterwards. Now you could say that maybe the renter
is a שומר shomer and these guys aren't שומרים, shomrim, right, and
so it's a different question from that perspective. Let's see what תוספות
Tosafot says. ויש לומר דהיכא דשני לא משלם, ve-yesh lomar de-heicha de-shinei
lo meshalem, the workers don't pay. דמרא דנא מסר את הפרה הוא
והשוכר את הפועלים, de-mara de-na masar et ha-parah hu ve-ha-socher et ha-poalim,
which is what we said, you hire the renters, okay, the owner
of the cow rents out the workers לילך עם פרתו ולעשות מלאכת
השוכר. leilech im parato ve-la'asot melechet ha-socher. ומשום הכי לא משלם, u-meshum
hachi lo meshalem, here's why the workers don't pay in this case,
דאמרו ליה למשכיר, de-amru lei le-maschir, they say to the renter, to
the owner, אנן לא התנינו עמך אלא לחרוש בבקעה, anan lo hitninu
imcha ela lachrosh ba-bik'ah, ולא קיבלנו שמירת הקנקן בהר אלא בבקעה. ve-lo
kibalnu shmirat ha-kankan ba-har ela ba-bik'ah. So we said look, when we
agreed to be rented out, we heard that the terms of the
agreement were to do it in the valley. So our responsibility was
to have the degree of care appropriate for valley plowing. Okay? So
our whole relationship to you was the degree of care appropriate for
those terms of the contract, okay? ומכל מקום שכירות שלנו לא נפסד,
u-micol makom schirut shelanu lo nifsad, but then listen to this, they
can turn around and say, and we still want to get paid
by the way. Okay? Why? כי בדבורך עשינו כמו שהשבת על שאלתינו,
ki be-diburacha asinu kemo she-heshavta al she'alateinu, you wanted us to listen
to him. We listened to him. It's almost like our contract, our
relationship, what we get paid for is by following his instructions and
we did that, so pay us. What we're responsible to you for
is for a degree of care appropriate for the original terms of
the contract. So it's like an interesting split. We didn't do what
the contract was, we were listening to him, but that's what we're
being paid for but not what our liability is to you.
You pay them for the whole job.
Yeah, you pay them for the job, exactly. Well, I don't know
if they... I don't know, that's a different question, that's sort of
like one of the earlier questions if the job ended in the
middle of the day. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara. goes back
to the גמרא. Gemara ודוכתא דמחזקא גונדרי. V'dukhta d'machzaka gundrei. Now let's
say it's a place where it's known that there are a lot
of, like you know, stones and whatever. Okay, so both of the
workers came in knowing that, you know, they needed to be extra
careful. In that case, תרוייהו משלמין, tarvay mshalmin, they both pay. Now
that's interesting because even though they know that it's a stony place,
so who cares? So they're both negligent. They were both negligent presumably
in the first case as well. Here there's just more negligence, right?
But still, why isn't it the second guy who pays? Why is
it that they both pay? So look at תוספות Tosafot again, ואי
דוכתא דמחזקינן בגונדרי תרוייהו משלמין, v'i dukhta d'michezkun b'gundrei tarvay mshalmin, פירש
בקונטרס משום דהוי ספק מי עשה, perish bakuntras b'shum d'havei safek mi
asa,
because in that case, you know, it's a
question who is more negligent? In this case maybe if you know
it's so rocky and you're the guy leading the cab, maybe you
have like maybe in that case you're even more negligent than me.
But תוספות Tosafot says one minute, ואין נראה דלא קיימא לן כסומכוס
אלא כרבנן והמוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, v'ein yeira, d'lo kayma lan k'sumchus
ela k'rabbanan v'hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya, in this case of doubt, then
neither of them should pay because then you can't prove who's negligent,
okay? ואי הוי ספק הוו שניהם פטורין, v'i havei safek havu shneihem
pturin, אלא נראה
לתוספות דתרווייהו פשעו, ella nirei l'tosafot d'trvayhu pash'u, they're both negligent, why?
כיון דמחזקא בגונדרי
הוא נשבר מאד בקל, kivun d'machzaka b'gundrei, hu nishpar me'od b'kal, right?
It's very likely that this thing is going to break. You have
to everybody goes in knowing we're going to need to be super
careful, okay? והיה לכל אחד ליתן לב, v'haya l'chol echad litten lev,
not so,
okay super careful, but nevertheless, like if we said it's the guy
in the back that's more liable, why isn't that true here? So
listen what he says. והיה לכל אחד ליתן לב על חבירו
כמו על עצמו
ולהזהירו ואחרי שלא הזהירו גם הוא פשע v'haya l'chol echad litten lev
al chaveiro k'mo al atzmo u'lehazhiro. Savi acharei shelo hizhiro gam hu
pasha. Since we both go in knowing we have to be super
careful, it doesn't just mean I have to be super careful at
my job. It means that we know that we're going to have
to be watching one another, okay? This is a really delicate operation,
so everybody's got to be really good at their job and also
everybody's got to watch out for everybody else, okay? And therefore even
if it's the guy in the back who we sort of say
is the proximate person, I'm partly negligent for his act, not just
for my act. And therefore I also pay. It's a powerful idea,
right? So under what circumstances, right, does it so big that not
just I have to be super careful for myself but it becomes
like a collective responsibility. Okay, so back to the גמרא. Gemara אמר
רבי יוחנן, amar Rabi Yochanan, המוכר פרה לחברו ואמר לו. hamocher para
l'chaveiro v'amar lo. Somebody sells a cow and says to his, this
isn't exactly the same case, not exactly clear why the גמרא's Gemara
throwing it in here, but whatever. Okay and says the cow sells
a cow to his friend and says, פרה זו נגחנית היא נשכנית
היא בעטנית היא
רבצנית היא. para zo natchanit hi, nashchanit hi, ba'atnit hi, rabetzanit hi.
Okay now I didn't just say one of these. Michael, I'm selling
you this cow, but I want you to know, it's a goring
cow, it bites, it kicks, and it crouches on things. Okay so
he tells you all these problems. Now והיתה בה מום אחד. v'hayta
ba mum echad. Now
the reality was one of those four things was present. וסינפו בין
המומין. v'sinfo bein hamumin. And I like appended it to all these
other things. I snuck in the real problem amongst these list of
fake problems. So you think that, רש"י says basically you think I'm
just listing all these things that aren't a problem to protect myself.
So if after you buy the cow and you say hey Dov
it turned out that it was A B and C I said
I told you it had all those problems, but you actually think
that this is just total boilerplate, it's a totally fine cow, and
I'm just saying this as a way to protect myself against future
complaints because I list ten problems and you look at it and
you can't imagine that it has all those problems and it doesn't
look like it has any of those problems, okay? But the reality
is it had one of them. I just hid the real problem
among the list. Okay, and now I can protect myself. So the
הלכה halacha is הרי
זה מקח טעות. harei zeh mekach taut. It's a מקח טעות mekach
taut because in that case you can say you were not, you
know, you did not really believe that it had any of those
problems and therefore you were not pre-informed. And if I sell you
a cow that actually has one, now it doesn't mean that anything
any little problem you can retract, but if it had any one
of these serious defects it was a מקח טעות. mekach taut. And
the only reason it was would not be a מקח טעות mekach
taut was so I could say I pre-warned you. Okay, so that's
the basic point. I sold you a cow סתם stam and it
had a serious defect, מקח טעות. mekach taut. Here I'm trying to
say I pre-warned you and the response is you did not pre-warn
me when you gave me that whole silly boilerplate, none of it
was serious, okay, I didn't take any of it seriously so that
doesn't count as pre-warning. Yes.
So if I were to say like you're buying it as is
with any defects, is that still not good enough because you're not
taking it seriously if it's...
No,
that's an interesting question. You're right like why isn't there a case
of as is? Well, it is sort of a case of as
is. You're right, that's a good parallel. Like, you know, these are
final sales, sold as is, whatever.
I wonder what happens if let's say, here's an example, you go
to a store and they're selling shirts that are like slightly irregular,
okay, at half price, as is. Okay, and you take it home
and you open up the package and there's a huge ink stain
on it, you know, that you couldn't see from the package. Say,
well, we said as is. this, you know? No, you know, there's
an as is of sort of what you expect in the as
is and there's something like you don't expect. So it's a good
point. I think that the point is that when somebody lists all
these crazy things, it's sort of like saying as is, but it
at the end of the day you don't expect a real big
defect. But that's exactly what the גמרא's Gemara dealing with, you know?
Even if I say as is, I don't plan on any defects
and there's one major defect, I can still say מקח טעות, mekach
taut, or whatever it was.
Right, so the interesting question about this is what if the owner
is not consciously doing this? I'm giving this boilerplate list, I don't
know if it has any problem, I'm not trying to hide a
problem. Right, that's a difference between like a sale where there's deceit
and a sale where there's an error but there's no deceit, right?
So I'm not trying to hide a problem but on the other
hand you're not knowing to be aware of a specific problem. So
that, I was wondering that as well, like would that be the
same as this case? Okay, but the basic point is that when
you say this big list, it's not taken seriously and specifically if
the person is using it to hide a problem and therefore it
still remains a מקח טעות. mekach taut.
It would be the same thing if I didn't say anything and
I knew it had a problem, I just didn't inform you.
Oh, that goes without saying. Here it's just a חידוש chiddush that
you said this list. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this:
מום זה ומום אחר אין זה מקח טעות. Mum zeh umum acher
ein zeh mekach taut. Now let's say I say to you, Michael,
this cow is a goring cow and it's got probably other- and
it's got other problems as well, okay? Since I only mentioned the
one and that was the one that it had the problem, so
maybe I threw in the other stuff to protect me but because
I
specifically singled out that one thing then it's not a מקח טעות.
mekach taut. Then you should've checked that one thing that I singled
out and you should've been aware that I was serious about it.
Partly what תוספות Tosafot also says about this is- and this isn't
clear from the גמרא- Gemara is that when I made this whole
list, right, the reason that it's not a מקח טעות mekach taut
is because you could say, look, I checked one of those things
and I saw it didn't have one, so I assumed it didn't
have any. Okay, now that would require that you actually did check,
okay? On the other hand, in this case, if I can say
it has this one thing, if you didn't bother to check the
one thing I singled out, you know, then that's your problem. Okay,
but the bottom line is because it was singled out, you had
to take it seriously.
It really reminds me of like those drug commercials, you know?
May cause this side
effect, that side effect.
Right, right, right, right. Anyway, the whole point though that you can
hide something by putting it with other things, it's like there was
this-
you know, there's a what do you call it, I think there's
like this Irish folk tale that somebody told me once when I
was giving a שיעור shiur on the principle of like, you know,
בל תוסיף וכל המוסיף גורע. bal tosif vechol hamosif goreia. So he
told me this story, you know, the guy catches a leprechaun. So
you catch a leprechaun, he has to show you the pot of
gold, right? So he brings him to this place in the forest,
right, and he shows him where the pot of gold is
hidden and he has to now go and get back his equipment
to dig it out, right? So he takes like- it's hidden underneath
this tree. So he takes a ribbon and he ties the ribbon
around the tree and he makes the leprechaun swear that he will
not take off the ribbon, right, when he goes back to get
his shovel. So he goes back to get his shovel, he comes
back and there's ribbons on every tree.
So there you go. So you hide it amongst everything else. Alright,
anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, good story, right? Alright,
the גמרא Gemara
says- alright, yes, true story. Okay, for this I was there.
Okay, הרי זה מקח טעות. Harei zeh mekach taut. מום זה ומום
אחר אין זה מקח טעות. Mum zeh umum acher ein zeh mekach
taut. תנו רבנן המוכר שפחה לחבירו, Tanu rabanan hamocher shifcha lechavero, okay,
a female slave. ואמר לו שפחה זו שוטה היא, Ve’amar lo shifcha
zu shota hi, she is crazy. נכפית היא, Nichpit hi, she has
epilepsy. משועממת היא, Meshu’amemet hi, which תוספות Tosafot says- the רש״י Rashi
says is like also type of crazy or the- I thought משועממת
meshu’amemet mean like boredom? Yes, she's lazy or something. והיה בה מום
אחד, Vehaya bah mum echad, so you list the whole list.
וסנפו בין המומים, Usnafo bein hamumim, and you
sort of and you know, appended it to all these other things,
inserted it in this whole list. הרי זה מקח טעות. Harei zeh
mekach taut. Then the person doesn't take any of the list seriously
and it was a real problem and it's a מקח טעות. mekach
taut. מום זה ומום אחר, Mum zeh umum acher, if you say
this particular one and you mention one other or you just say
this one and others. אין זה מקח טעות, Ein zeh mekach taut,
it's not because since this one was singled out, it is something
that he should've checked. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי,
Amar lei Rav Acha brei deRava leRav Ashi, Rav Acha son of
Rava said to Rav Ashi. היו בו כל המומים הללו מהו? Hayu
vo kol hamumim halalu mahu?
Let's say it actually had all of those things.
What's the question? Because I still think you're just being silly. You're
just saying this to protect yourself. What type of a cow has
all those problems? So I don't take anything you're
saying seriously. Okay, so alright, but let's see what the answer is.
So אמר ליה רב מרדכי לרב אשי הכי אמרו משמיה דרבא היו
בו כל המומים הללו אין זה מקח טעות. Amar lei Rav Mordechai
leRav Ashi hachi amru mishmeih deRava hayu vo kol hamumim halalu ein
zeh mekach taut. It's not a מקח טעות. mekach taut. So part
of you're saying you couldn't design anything more or you could've made
it that I'm really serious, come let me show you. Or, but
תוספות Tosafot says again, that I the buyer
could've checked any one of those and seen that it was accurate.
So therefore, if I didn't bother checking anything on that list that's
my fault. Okay next משנה.
Mishna השוכר את
החמור להביא
Hasocher et hachamor
lehavi so it's really a matter of you checking?
In other words that's why תוספות Tosafot frames it. That's not clear
but that's part of what תוספות Tosafot brings into the factor. השוכר
את החמור להביא עליה חטים והביא עליה שעורים. Hasocher et hachamor lehavi
aleha chitin vehevi aleha seorim. You rented a donkey to bring wheat
and instead you brought barley. And barley is lighter than wheat. Okay.
להביא עליה חטים והביא עליה שעורים חייב. Lavi aleha chitin vehevi aleha
seorim chayav.
Then you are חייב chayav. because why? Oh because the assumption...
wait a minute let me get this straight.
Yeah, the barley is lighter. So why you חייב chayav. if you
brought the barley? I mean you actually brought less of a load.
But the point is you actually brought and we'll see the more
specifics in the גמרא Gemara but you actually brought the same amount
of weight. Okay? I said I'm going to take ten pounds of
wheat and I took ten pounds of barley which is lighter.
So what did I do?
No, well, ten pounds...
right, which weighs more? Right, a pound of feathers or a pound
of lead? They both weigh the same. So I said ten pounds
of wheat and I brought ten pounds of barley but barley is
less dense, it's lighter per volume. So what did I do wrong
when I brought ten pounds of barley?
I had
extra volume. Exactly. So the extra volume means that I violated the
terms of the agreement and therefore I'm liable. If the... for what?
For the donkey. The donkey trips and breaks its leg.
Right, assumption from the last משנה.
Mishna Right, so donkey, exactly. Something happened to the donkey. Okay. חייב.
chayav. תבואה והביא עליה תבן Tevua vehevi aleha teven or similarly I
say grain and I bring straw which is lighter. חייב. chayav. מפני
שהנפח קשה כמשוי Mipnei shehanepach kashe kimasoi
because volume, נפח, nefach, right, is difficult like a weight. So it's
going to be a debate exactly what this means but for here
we'll sort of say increased volume is a similar problem as increased
weight. So the same way if you go beyond the weight limit
that was agreed to, if you go beyond the volume that was
implied by that weight limit, you've also violated the terms. What about
the other way around? No, more weight is clearly... What do you
mean not more weight? Like you say I'm going to bring three
bags
of straw and you bring three bags of grain? So of course
you're חייב.
chayav, שעורים והביא עליה חטים Seorim vehevi aleha chitin for ten pounds
but now שעורים seorim is more volume. Now the same weight but
less volume.
So that's fine. What do you mean? Right, of course. Okay, the
problem is when it's more. Okay, so if you say a certain
weight and you bring the same weight of something less dense, you
violate by doing more volume. If you say a certain volume and
you bring the same volume of something more dense, you violate by
adding more weight. שהנפח קשה כמשוי. Shehanepach kashe kimasoi. להביא לתך חטים.
Lehavi letach chitin. Now to bring a לתך letach of חטים. chitin.
A לתך letach is a lot, it's like
thirty קבים... kabim... no, thirty סאה, seah, excuse me. Okay? So I
looked this up last night. A קב kav is... hold on, I'll
tell you.
But I think
his לתך letach is... it's
fifteen סאה. seah. What? It'd be fifteen סאה. seah. Because a כור
kor equals thirty סאה seah and a לתך letach here says is
half a כור. kor. Hold on. It should be fifteen סאה. seah.
Hold on.
Let's look inside here.
I wonder if this is like the U-Haul and they have a
weight limit and you over... it's not. Right.
Hold on. Animal right activists protesting this.
Okay.
So now here if these are volume measures, okay?
חברה, chevre, the following is volume measures. Okay. So...
Okay. So a סאה... seah...
a
סאה seah is about one and a half liters. Okay? So have
you seen the top of like a one and a half liter
bottle of soda? So that's approximately what a סאה seah is. Okay?
A...
and that is equal to six קב. kav. Okay? So there are...
how would I do this?
Anyway... okay... is six קב. kav. Anyway, it's one and a half
liter. So a קב kav is how much? Anyway, fine. Okay. And
then and then there are... one minute... a לתך letach is fifteen
סאה, seah, so that's what David was saying. And a כור kor
is two לתך. letach. Okay?
Or thirty סאה. seah.
Or thirty סאה. seah. Okay, and this is fifteen סאה, seah, which
is I guess ninety קב. kav.
All right? So anyway, that's basically the arrangement. Now, so you said
you were going to take a לתך letach of grain, which is
about... so the לתך letach is
fifteen. So, להביא לתך letech חיטים *L'havi Letech Chitim*, you are going
to bring לתך letech, חיטים *letech chitim*,
okay, like those 15 soda bottles' worth, okay? דהביא לתך letech, שעורים
se'orim, *Dehavi Letech Se'orim*, and you brought that volume of שעורים *se'orim*.
פטור *patur*, you're פטור *patur*, obviously. Same volume, less weight. והוסיף על
משאו חייב chayav. *V'hosif al masao chayav*. Now, if you add weight,
you're חייב chayav, *chayav*. So if you add weight and add volume,
you're חייב chayav *chayav*. You keep the volume and it's less dense,
obviously you're not חייב chayav? *chayav*. If you add weight, even if
you don't add volume, obviously you will be חייב chayav. *chayav*. Okay.
וכמה יוסיף על משאו ויהיה חייב chayav, *V'chama yosif al masao v'yiyeh
chayav*? How much weight would adding make you חייב chayav *chayav*? סומכוס
אומר משום רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. סאה se'ah *Sumchus omer mishum Rabbi
Meir se'ah*. סאה se'ah, *se'ah*. Now, you agreed to do a לתך
letech. *letech*, which is, wait, you agreed לתך letech. *letech*, right, which
is a סאה se'ah *se'ah*, which is 1/15th. If you increase the
amount agreed by by 1/15th, you're חייב Chayav. *chayav*. רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir *Rabbi Meir*,
I'm sorry, סאה sa'ah. לגמל שלושה קבים לחמור *se'ah l'gamal shlosha kabim
l'chamor*. And for a camel is, you know, camel basically can, well
we'll actually see how much you originally agreed. But here we're going
back to the donkey case. The donkey case, you said that you
were going to do a לתך letech *letech*, and it says that
if you did three, if you did three קב kav, *kav*, okay?
So you agreed to do a לתך letech, *letech* for the donkey.
We don't know how much, right, we don't know how much you
agreed for the camel. But talking about the donkey, the case was
you agreed to do a לתך *letech*, which is 90 קב kab,
*kav*. And if you increase that by three קב Kav. *kav*, which
is one,
an increase of 1/30th, that's considered to be that you violated your
agreement. You can't go 1/30th over the weight that you agreed upon,
okay? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s basic assumption in the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* whatever, is that that's true regardless of the person or the
animal that's doing the שלעפינג *shlepping*. So if for example we say
that the allowable overage for a camel is, you know, is whatever,
is
סאה sa'ah, *se'ah*, then that means that a camel can actually, which
is six קב kav. *kav*, then that means that a camel can
actually carry 30 times that, right, which is like 180 קב kav
*kav*. Whatever the overage is, we assume that the overage represents a
30th of what the normal sort of tolerable weight for that thing
is. So if we're saying the acceptable overage for a for a
donkey, right, if the acceptable overage for a donkey is is is
שלושה סאה *shlosha se'ah*,
then we're saying that's the overage, then we're saying that its tolerable
weight limit is 90 סאה *se'ah*. Okay, which is a לתך *letech*,
right, a לתך *letech* was 15, I mean, not 90, excuse me,
three קב kav, *kav*. I'm getting too confused like this, 90 קב
kav, *kav*.
Wait, how much weight did the camel, why does he go backwards?
Well,
no, you did say. Meaning, meaning you said we agreed that you
could carry, meaning a, there's one general interesting question, which is if
you didn't say specifically is there a presumed default for certain animals?
Right, but the case in the משנה *Mishnah* was was that you
agreed that it could carry, that you were going to do it
for a לתך *letech*. And the משנה *Mishnah* for a donkey, and
the משנה *Mishnah* is telling you acceptable overage for a לתך *letech*,
which is 90, which is 90 קב kav. *kav* is three קב
kav *kav*. But from that we infer that the general accepted overage
is 1/30th. Right. Okay. So should we assume also in
terms of volume then that there is some leeway?
So that's going to be an interesting question. Let's say you kept
the weight and you increased the volume, how much is there like,
is there a little bit of volume that you can still, a
little bit of acceptable overage, right? So let's look at the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. איתמר *Itmar*, we said, אביי Abaye אמר קשה כמשאוי תנן
tenan, *Abaye amar kasha k'masao tnan*, that the volume, increased volume is
as is like increased weight, it's as difficult as increased weight. ורבא
אמר קשה למשאוי תנן *V'Rava amar kasha l'masao tnan*. No, no, no,
it's not making an equivalency. It's saying that increased volume,
you know, makes the burden harder of the for the animal. But
it doesn't tell you how to measure the impact of increased volume.
You understand the difference? אביי Abaye. *Abaye* is saying the measure of
increased volume is measured the same way that increased weight is measured.
רבא Rava *Rava* is just saying no, by increasing the volume you
make the burden for the donkey more difficult, but you're not saying
exactly what you're doing. Okay.
Now, so the קשיא *kashya* is like this. So אביי Abaye, אמר
קשה כמשאוי תנן נפחא כתיקלא *Abaye amar kasha k'masao tnan napcha k'tikla*,
volume is like weight. והוסיף שלושה קבים חייב *V'hosif shlosha kabim chayav*.
So the same way by weight when you go three קב kav
*kav* over of weight you're חייב *chayav*, so כאן *kan* by the
way the interesting thing here is that קב kav *kav* is a
volume measure, okay? So all these measures I put up on the
board are volume measures. So if I basically said to, you know,
I lent I lent out my donkey to Jenna to carry a
לתך *letech*, which is, you know, which is 90, which is 90
קב kav. *kav*, and and 90 קב kav *kav* is a volume
measure. Okay, we'll call it 90 liters, alright, of wheat. So she
can't go over, she can't have an overage more than three liters
of wheat. Okay, similarly, so it's interesting. The problem is weight, but
we're measuring it by volume. Alright. So therefore, if she went, if
she actually chose barley, which was lighter, and she went over three
liters, right, it's the same problem. I, the overage is, what we
were initially concerned about weight, and we were assuming a certain weight
because we were assuming wheat, and we measured the overage was defined
in terms of how much volume are you going to go over.
Don't take three extra bags of wheat. Let's talk about it as
if it were bags. You're going to take 90 bags of wheat.
That's a certain weight. You're not allowed to take, if you went
over, you'll be violated when you've taken three extra bags, okay? So
if you, even if you took barley and it weighed less, you
violate when you take three extra bags, okay, because the increased volume
is just as problematic as the increased weight. All right. So now
that's the way אביי Abaye says it. רבא אמר לא קשה למסוי
תנן. Rava amar lo kashe le-masoi tenan. No, no,
no, increased volume makes it more difficult, but it's not the same
way to measure. תקלא כתקלא, takla ke-takla, okay, the weight,
when the weight is equivalent, that's when it's a problem, ונפחא הוי
תוספת. ve-nafcha havei tosefet. So רבא Rava is much more lenient, I
guess, for the renter. רבא Rava says volume does not start to
be a problem as long as your the weight is less. Okay,
volume is like a very amorphous problem. So when the, so it's
an in, it's so it's just enough to be a violation by
itself. So if, you know, I agreed to 30 bags of wheat
and I took 45 bags of barley, and that even, that weighed
less than 30 bags of wheat, according to רבא Rava I'm פטור.
But when, but if 46 bags of barley equals the weight of
the wheat, then I'm חייב. Why? Because I've increased volume. So do
you understand? For רבא Rava, the point is, if your weight is
exactly the limit, then the increased volume is a violation. But if
your weight is under the limit, then we can't get hold you
for the increased volume. All right. So רבא, Rava it's a much
bigger leniency. אביי Abaye. just says, I just look, I don't care
what's in the bags. I don't care if it's lighter or heavier.
I treat it as if it's the original weight and if you
have more volume you violated. Okay. Whereas רבא Rava says no, no,
no. It only begins to be a problem once the weight is
the same. All right. So now the גמרא gemara says like this,
תנן, let's see who this works like.
להביא לתך חיטים והביא לתך שעורים פטור, le-havi letach chitim ve-hevi letach
se'orim patur, ואם הוסיף על משאו חייב. ve-im hosif al masao chayav.
So you now brought the same amount of barley, you're exempt, but
if you add you're חייב. Now that sounds like, you have the
same 30 bags now of barley rather than of wheat, and it
sounds like any addition now, any overage is going to be חייב,
right, the standard overage of the, you know,
of the three bags? You have 90 bags and then any overage
of the three bags you're going to be
חייב. מאי לאו שלושה קבין? mai lav shelosha kabin? That sounds like
as soon as you have the equivalent, as soon as you have
the same volume, the standard overage rules apply. And that sounds like
אביי. Abaye So you have the 90 bags, it's barley, it's not
wheat, but it's the same 90 bags, and it says any addition
you're חייב, meaning the standard overage, the three
קבין. kavin. I keep saying סאה when I mean to say קב,
kav I'm sorry if I'm confusing you. I'm going to say bags.
We're going to do a 90 bags. Okay, so it sounds like
the three, once you have the same volume, the same laws of
the three bags overage apply. So the גמרא Gemara says לא סאה.
lo se'ah. No, no, no, three would not be enough. You would
need a סאה, which is six. Okay, presumably once you're six bags
over it weighs the same, and now that it weighs the same,
now you're חייב for the increased volume. All right. So the גמרא
Gemara says והא קתני, ve-ha katani, one minute, we taught that וכמה
יוסיף על משאו ויהא חייב, ve-khama yosif al masao ve-yehe chayav, how
much would you add and you'd be חייב? סומכוס אומר משום רבי
מאיר סאה לגמל שלושה קבין לחמור, Sumchos omer mishum Rabbi Meir se'ah
le-gamal shelosha kabin le-chamor, that it's a סאה for a camel but
it's three bags for a donkey. So it sounds like we're talking
about a case that you brought barley, it weighs less, it's the
same amount of bags, and it sounds like it's the same rule,
three bags over you're חייב. So that sounds like אביי, Abaye that
it really doesn't matter what's in the bags, it all, you know,
it's all treated the same. So the גמרא Gemara says לא הכי
קאמר. lo hachi ka-amar. No, no, this is how to read it.
היכא דלא שני חיטים והביא חיטים שעורים והביא שעורים, heicha de-lo shani
chitim ve-hevi chitim se'orim ve-hevi se'orim, if you did not make a
change, you said wheat and you brought wheat, barley and you brought
barley, כמה יוסיף על משאו ויהא חייב, kama yosif al masao ve-yehe
chayav,
in that case when you did the right thing that you contracted,
how much overage are you allowed? In that case סומכוס אומר משום
רבי מאיר סאה לגמל שלושה קבין לחמור. Sumchos omer mishum Rabbi Meir
se'ah le-gamal shelosha kabin le-chamor. So if it's the same density and
everything is the same and the volume. is the same, that's when
it's a three-kab limit of three kabs over. Okay, when however it
is something lighter, then according to, so according to אביי's Abaye same
rule. I don't care if it's lighter, I don't care, doesn't matter.
You have your ninety kabs, three over, you're חייב, I don't care
if it's lighter or heavier. Okay, that's אביי. Abaye רבא Rava says,
no, no, no, the if it's lighter then you're no problems until
you've hit the weight limit. Once you hit the weight limit, then
we get you for the increased volume. But until then, no problem,
and you'll hit the weight limit when you go six kabs over
in the barley wheat case. That happens to be the reality. Okay,
did you have a question, Jenna?
Just if it's the same barley and it's the same volume. Right.
So it's the same weight of barley, I mean.
No, it's not the same weight. No, barley isn't. Barley is lighter.
No, no, I mean barley to barley. If you like brought.
Oh, no, no, so that's to clarify. When you said barley and
you brought barley, you're חייב when you do the three extra kabs
because of the weight increase. When the overage is three, if it's
purely a weight issue. You did exactly what you were supposed to,
but you brought, it's like, you know, you're going on the airplane,
right? It has to fit in a certain thing and it has
to weigh a certain thing.
If you say barley and you were supposed to bring barley and
you're fitting in the volume that you were supposed to have, but
you go over the weight because barley weighs the same as barley.
That's what I don't understand, how you?
Oh, you mean you're also going over the volume when you go
over the weight?
Yeah, I don't see how you could go over the weight without
going over the volume.
You, you are, you are going over both, but clearly the weight
is the thing that is the more obvious problem. Yeah, but we're
not interested in the volume if we can get you for the
weight. The weight is the bigger problem, right? So if you say
barley and you brought barley and you brought more, then the first
thing to focus on is that the burden weighed more. Okay, but
the basic definition is three extra kabs, that's too much overage. Okay,
so the question is when it's barley, when you said wheat and
you brought barley and it's less, so אביי Abaye says, I don't
care. Once it's the, once it's the three extra, you know, once
it's the, you had the ninety kabs you agreed on, I don't
care if it's barley or wheat, three more is overage end of
story, because I'm just as ready to look through a lens of
volume as I will through a lens of weight. And רבא Rava,
says, no, no, no, as long as the weight is less, you're
fine. Once the weight is the same, we חאפ chap you on
the volume. Yeah.
I just want to make sure I'm understanding what you wrote on
the board. You have there one לתך is one and a half
סאה. No,
fifteen.
Okay.
Okay. All right.
This is like the luggage on the plane. Exactly. If the bag
is too heavy, you get dinged.
Too heavy you get dinged, right.
Too big of a bag or you need, right.
But there's separate criteria. Here the problem was we're sort of conflating
it. We have one that's the primary and we're sort of conflating
the other into it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara. says like this.
תא שמע, Ta shma, come and hear. להביא לתך חטים והביא שש
עשרה שעורים. Lehavi letech chitim veheivi sheish esreih se'orim.
You said you were going to bring a לתך, and you brought,
which is
fifteen סאה, and you brought sixteen of שעורים, okay? Now that's one
fifteenth increment. That's a bigger increment, right, than normally. Normally you're, you
know, we get you when it's one thirtieth increment. Here we're going
to get you only when it's one fifteenth of an increment, right?
We give you more latitude. חייב. Okay,
so that sounds like why are we giving you more latitude? Because
you were dealing with a lighter load. So it sounds like רבא,
Rava. that when actually it's a lighter load, we don't חאפ chap
you as soon as it's one thirtieth over. We're only going to
חאפ chap you when it's one fifteenth over. Okay? הא שלשה קבין
פטור. Ha sheloshah kabin patur. If it was only three קב, kav
you'd be exempt. So in the look, this supports רבא. Rava When
it's barley, right, we don't חאפ chap you immediately when it's one
thirtieth over. We're only going to חאפ chap you when it's a
fifteenth. So תרגמה אביי, Targemah Abaye, אביי says no, במחיקתא. bimechiktsa.
So what does במחיקתא bimechiktsa mean? There's a debate. Does that mean
that it's extra light barley? So if it's extra light barley, there
are times that אביי won't treat volume the same as weight if
the stuff is particularly light. Or does it mean במחיקתא bimechiktsa means
like a very precisely measured as opposed to like a generously measured.
You know, how much do you measure it like very, you know,
everything exact flat or whatever, how much, yeah, you know, a stuffed
bag, doesn't have to be exact flat bag. Okay, depends how nice
the guy behind the counter is when he's trying to get the
bag on the plane. Right. So, so אביי says you know, no,
actually it really is a problem when it's three, but three, you
know, when it's
three over but three over measured generously, which is six over, you
know, measured not generously or whatever.
Anyway, the רש"י is really interesting on this word.
Yeah, I know but I don't want to get into it. תנו
רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, we're behind. קב לכתף. Kav lachateif. Okay, so anyway
that's the debate of אביי and רבא whether you have whether it's
basically volume is the same issue or it's just some abstract additional
problem. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabbanan. קב לכתף. Kav lachateif. Now how about
for somebody who's a personal schlepper, a person? So how much is
his acceptable overage? קב. kav, Okay, which means that an animal can
take a לתך, which is an animal's overage. is three קב. Okay,
a donkey, a donkey's overage
is three, a person's overage is
one, and a camel's overage is six. Okay, which means that a
donkey
can carry
ninety קב
or ninety קב, a person can carry thirty קב, and a donkey
can carry a hundred and eighty קב. And what did we say
a קב was? Well, if you divide by six, if you divide
by six, then you get my bottles of soda. So that's actually
quite light for a person because thirty קב is really
only what?
Thirty קב is really only like no, no, no, the over... this
is the overage. The overage is one bottle of soda is one
קב. But there are, but you know, but six קב for one
of those one and a half liter bottles of soda. I mean
you guess if you filled it with wheat, still doesn't seem so
big, right?
Thirty קב would be
my five soda bottles, okay, filled with wheat. So I think even
I, who am not in the world's best shape, could probably שלעפ
schlep more than five soda bottles worth of wheat, but I don't
know, maybe it would be like really heavy. What? Yeah, anyway. Exactly.
Good point too! You're right. How far am I carrying it? Okay,
so anyway קב לכתף, kav lekatef, so a porter, one קב over
is a problem.
אדריב לארבה. adriv l'arevah. Now if an ארבה arevah is a small
little raft boat, so how much can a boat carry? How much
is overage for a boat? Like overage for a plane, right? So
רש״י Rashi says אדריב, adriv, רש״י Rashi says means a what do
you call it?
רש״י Rashi says an אדריב adriv is a לתך. It's another word
for a לתך. So one לתך overage for a boat, which means
a boat can carry thirty לתך, and כור לספינה. kor l'sfina. One
כור kor overage for
a
boat, for a medium sized boat. שלשה כורים לבורני גדולה shlosha korim
l'vurni gedola and three כור kor overage for a big ship. Okay,
אמר מר. amar mar. So now let's unpack this. קב לכתף. kav
lekatef. So for a person, you know, one extra קב, right, so
one-sixth of a soda bottle, that's considered overage, right? Which is pretty
small. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says one minute, how can you go
ahead and and you know I used to be a שלעפער schlepper
for you, you put too much weight on my back, you went
over, and I'm saying to you you know you have to pay
for my doctor bill, I tripped I injured myself, you have to
pay because you put because of the overage. Why didn't I do
something about it, right? You know when I saw you were putting
too much, like I accepted it. If I let you put too
much on me, okay, it's not like you rented my donkey and
you put on it without me knowing. You put this on my
back.
But we're not talking about slaves we're talking about...
Right. People who rent themselves out as porters, right?
אי אשתדו לא מצי ביה, ee ishtadu lo matzi beih, if I
realized when you put that overage on me that I couldn't handle
it, so בר דעת הוא, bar da'atu, so I'm an intelligent person,
ושדיה, ushadiye, let me just throw it off me. How can I
now go and blame you? If I was willing to accept it,
I implicitly agreed to accept it. So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, בשחבטו
לאלתר. beshachavtu l'alter. As soon as you put it on I collapsed.
Okay, so therefore, and therefore, I can't you can't say, oh, well,
you know, Dov, you you saw I was putting on extra and
you were okay with it. As soon as you put it on
I had an injury. Wait a minute, רבא אמר אפילו תימא ושלא
חבטו לאלתר. Rava amar afilu teima v'shelo chavtu l'alter. Even if the
injury didn't happen immediately, לא צריכא אלא לאגרא יתירה. lo tzricha ela
l'agra yeseira.
Fine, I implicitly agreed to it, so I don't get have a
complaint to you that like you caused me injury, but now I
can charge you extra. I can say, hey, you put extra on
my back, fine I agreed to it, the same way I implicitly
agree to take extra, you implicitly agreed to pay for extra. So
רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, הוא סבר כושיא הוא דנקיט ליה.
hu savar kusha hu denakit leh. No, no, no. I could feel
that it's felt heavy. But I didn't know that that's because you
put more than we agreed. I assumed you put what we agreed.
I thought, you know, maybe I didn't get a good night's sleep
last night. So I didn't realize that that was the problem that
I should do something about it. I never accepted it and it
was your fault. Okay.
I mean would you really be able to tell someone put like
an extra...
Right. So that's an interesting question. I think so. It's a small
amount. It's a one-thirtieth increase. I don't know. Anyway, but it's interest,
it's interesting like who has a responsibility to be watching and measuring
and determining. Okay, so רב אשי... Rav Ashi... okay. So כור לספינה,
kor l'sfina, שלשה כורים לבורני גדולה. shlosha korim l'vurni gedola. אמר רב
פפא שמע מינה סתם ספינה בת תלתין כורין. amar Rav Pappa shma
mina stam sfina bat tlatin korin. So because we're assuming it's one-thirtieth,
if a כור kor is an acceptable overage for a boat, a
standard boat has to have to be able to support thirty כור.
kor. למאי נפקא מינה למקח וממכר. lemai nafka mina l'mekach u'mimkar. The
relevance is if you buy a boat, and you know, and then
it's presumed that it has storage facilities for thirty כור kor and
if not then
the...
Right, but then
you have no complaint, because if you needed work that bad that
you were willing to go against the normal, you know, the normal
parameters, then fine, those were the agreements. Don't complain to me. כל
אומנין שומר שכר הן. Kol umanin shomer sachar hen. Craftsmen. What's up?
What?
Yeah, that's true. So that's an interesting question. You know, is there
anything in הלכה Halacha that prevents people from contracting for very disadvantageous
things if they need the money? So that's an important question. Okay,
כל אומנין שומר שכר הן. Kol umanin shomer sachar hen. All craftsmen
are שומר שכר. shomer sachar. I give you my wood to go
build a box for me, and then something happens to the wood,
like not you broke it, some גנבים ganavim snuck in or something
like that. Okay, you're a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. Now why are
you a שומר שכר? shomer sachar? I am paying you, but I'm
not paying you to watch it, I'm paying you to turn it
into a into a box. But maybe the fact that... so this
is what the גמרא Gemara is going to figure out. Maybe the
fact that I'm giving you employment is considered like a benefit you
get from me. You know, what is the additional benefit you're getting
from me rather than the trade of my money for your labor?
What's the additional pay you're getting that makes you a שומר שכר?
shomer sachar? So the גמרא Gemara is going to figure that out.
Okay, וכולן שאמרו טול את שלך והבא מעות שומר חנם. Vekulan she'amru
tol et shelcha vehavei maot shomer chinam. But as soon as you
call me up and say, "Dov, your thing is ready, come take
it away, okay, and pay me you know and pay me," you
know, then you're a שומר חנם. shomer chinam. The גמרא Gemara is
going to say, but if you said, "First pay me, after you
pay me you can come take it," then you're still in your
then you're still like in your you know as an אומן uman
and you're still in that capacity and you're still a שומר שכר.
shomer sachar. But once you say, "No, no, no, you can pick
it up immediately, you'll pay me after," okay, and you're not holding
it until I pay you, then you've basically employment has ended and
now you're just a שומר חנם. shomer chinam. שמור לי ואשמור לך
שומר שכר. Shemor li ve'eshmor lecha shomer sachar. If I say, "David,
watch my you know watch my knapsack here, I gotta run do
a thing and I'll watch your knapsack tomorrow, I know you have
you have to do something," then we're שומר שכר shomer sachar for
one another. We're paying each other for you know for the service
that we're doing in exchange, right? Which is funny you know because
you could have said that we're just doing favors and we're שומרי
חנם, shomrei chinam, right, and we're just reciprocating favors. But we're translating
it as a type of a payment. I'm paying you with my
שמירה, shmira, you're paying me with your שמירה. shmira. Okay, שמור לי
ואמר לו הנח לפני שומר חנם. Shemor li ve'amar lo hanach lefanai
shomer chinam. If I say, "David, watch my knapsack, I gotta go
run do something," he says, "Put it down." Okay, so you never
said yes, you just said, "Put it down." Okay, so שומר חנם.
shomer chinam. Now the חידוש chiddush there is you could have said
you're not a שומר shomer at all. You just said, "Put it
down," you didn't say yes. Okay, המלווה על המשכון שומר שכר. Hamalveh
al hamashkon shomer sachar.
Let's say I lend you money and you give me some collateral.
My responsibility to that collateral is and then some the collateral broke.
You gave me your iPhone to watch as collateral to give it
as collateral for the loan and it broke. I'm a שומר שכר.
shomer sachar. So what's my שכר? sachar? What was I getting paid
to watch it? רבי יהודה אומר המלווה מעות שומר חנם. Rabbi Yehuda
omer hamalveh maot shomer chinam. No, no, no. Normally lender money and
you're watching and you have the collateral, you're a שומר חנם. shomer
chinam. המלווה פירות שומר שכר. Hamalveh peirot shomer sachar. If I lent
you fruit, and how can you lend fruit? That's סאה בסאה, se'ah
bese'ah, that's a whole last perek, but we won't worry about that
right now. I'm a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. Why am I a
שומר שכר? shomer sachar? Because I'm lending you fresh apples, and in
a week from now you're going to give me back fresh apples.
So you actually did me a favor because you know because those
apples would have gone bad had you not you know if they'd
been sitting around in my house. So ironically, it's almost seen like
you a little bit did me a favor by borrowing it because
it could have spoiled. Okay, so then because of that favor I'm
a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. אבא שאול אומר רשאי אדם להשכיר משכונו
של עני להיות פוסק והולך עליו מפני שהוא כמשיב אבידה. Abba Shaul
omer rashai adam lehaskir mashkono shel ani lihyot posek veholech alav mipnei
shehu kemeshiv aveida. If I've got here David's iPhone and David's very
poor and I don't know if he's ever going to be able
to pay back my loan, then what I can do is I
could rent out his iPhone on a daily basis, you know, and
use all the proceeds from it to pay off David's loan. So
I can use his משכון mashkon and rent it out presumably without
his permission in order a way to pay off his loan for
his behalf. Okay, so it's pretty interesting. I mean, we understand it's
nice for David, but it's giving me a lot of liberties there.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara Let's just get started.
לימא מתניתין דלא כרבי מאיר. Leima matnitin dela kerabbi Meir.
Let's say our משנה that says an אומן uman is a שומר
שכר shomer sachar is not like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. דתניא Detanya
we learned in a ברייתא braita שוכר כיצד משלם. Socher keitzad meshalem.
How about a renter? A renter is like an אומן uman in
the following way: money changes hands, okay, but it's for an equal
exchange. I'm paying you for your car. So you're not so but
what makes him שומר שכר? shomer sachar? What benefit did I get
from you? I got a benefit that you gave me your car,
but I paid for that benefit. Okay, so I'm benefiting from you
but I paid for it. Am I a שומר שכר shomer sachar
or not? And the same is true by an אומן. uman. I'm
paying you to build me a box. You got something from me,
my pay, but that's because of an exchange because you're giving me
your labor. But because of the fact that you're getting my pay
still make you a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara assumes that an אומן uman and a שוכר socher would be
the same thing. שרבי מאיר SheRabbi Meir says... so what's a law
about a renter? כיצד משלם רבי מאיר. Keitzad meshalem Rabbi Meir. כיצד
השוכר רבי מאיר אומר כשומר חינם. Keitzad hasocher Rabbi Meir omer keshomer
chinam. He's a שומר חינם Shomer Chinam on the car. He's paying
for the rental of the car and he's a שומר חינם Shomer
Chinam on the car. רבי יהודה אומר כשומר שכר. Rabbi Yehuda omer
keshomer sachar. No, no, no, it's like he's a paid guardian. So
this sound, we're assuming an אומן Uman is like a שוכר. Socher.
It sounds like that this משנה that says he's a שומר שכר
Shomer Sachar goes like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says a שוכר
Socher is a שומר שכר. Shomer Sachar. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, אפילו תימא רבי מאיר. Afilu teima Rabbi Meir. An אומן Uman
is not necessarily like a שוכר. Socher. A שוכר Socher could be
a שומר חינם. Shomer Chinam. But here's the extra benefit the אומן
Uman gets that makes him a שומר שכר. Shomer Sachar. Okay, what
is the extra benefit the אומן Uman gets? בההיא הנאה דקשביק כולי
עלמא ואגר ליה לדידי. Behahi hana'ah dekashebik kulei alma ve'agar lei ledidi.
I gave you employment. The benefit that I gave you employment, yes
you're working for it, but you know it's not an easy economy
out there, you're very grateful to have the job. So the fact
that I gave you that employment, that makes you a שומר, Shomer,
that benefit makes you a שומר שכר Shomer Sachar on my wood.
הוי ליה שומר שכר. Havei lei shomer sachar. So the גמרא Gemara
says אי הכי, I hachi, so use the same logic by a
שוכר. Socher. שוכר נמי. Socher nami. בההיא הנאה דקשביק כולי עלמא ומוגר
ליה לדידי. Behahi hana'ah dekashebik kulei alma umogar lei ledidi. The fact
that you're not renting out to anybody else but you're renting out
to me, הוי ליה שומר שכר. Havei lei shomer sachar. That's a
benefit to me. Now of course that's bizarre because you're in the
business of renting and making money, you'd be happy to rent to
anyone, right? And a person's need for employment tends to usually be
greater than a person's need to be able to rent something. I
don't know, you need to rent a donkey because it's part of
your job maybe not, but nevertheless it seems a little bizarre. You
can really hear the גמרא Gemara that the favor you do for
somebody to give them employment is different, you know, than the favor
the renter does to rent you his car.
Alright, אלא אפילו תימא רבי מאיר. Ela afilu teima Rabbi Meir. Okay
fine, let's make the distinction this way. בההיא הנאה דקיהיב ליה טפי
פורתא Behahi hana'ah deka'yahiv lei tefi purta הוי ליה שומר שכר. havei
lei shomer sachar. So okay, but you know what, when I pay
you for your for building the box, you know, we like round
up, I'm not going to be super precise so there'll probably be
a little bit extra included in it. So that makes you a
שומר שכר. Shomer Sachar. So the גמרא says okay then that should
work the other way also. שוכר נמי. Socher nami. By case of
a rental by a car, מי לא עסקינן דקמשוי ליה טפי פורתא?
Mi lo askinan dekamashvi lei tefi purta? Maybe I'm also giving you
a little bit of a deduction, you know, I'm renting it to
you at a little bit of a reduced rate. Like why do
we assume that there's some extra money changing hands here, you know,
and why do we assume it in one case and not in
the other case? So that doesn't make sense. אלא Ela fine, let's
try it this way. אפילו תימא רבי מאיר, Afilu teima Rabbi Meir,
even with רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, what he says about that a
שוכר Socher is a שומר חינם, Shomer Chinam, here's why an אומן
Uman gets extra benefit. בההיא הנאה דתפיס ליה אאגרא, Behahi hana'ah detafis
lei a'agra, and this is what the גמרא concludes with. Because you're
holding my box and the fact is you can hold that until
you get paid. So that's the benefit you get, that you have
a way of making sure that you get paid. Okay, I paid
you for your work, you gave me your labor, that was an
equal exchange. Now you have leverage on me to get the money
that I owe you then that makes, by holding on the box.
So that benefit you get from holding on to the box that
you can use it as leverage, that makes you a שומר שכר
Shomer Sachar on the box. Okay דלא בעי למיזל ולמיפק אזוזי, Dela
ba'ei lemizlei ulemifak azuzei, you don't have to run after me for
the money, you got that leverage, הוי ליה שומר שכר. havei lei
shomer sachar. Which doesn't apply when I rent your car. When I
rent your car you don't have any leverage on me to make
sure that I'm going to pay you or anything like that or
I don't have any leverage on you. Okay, so there's no benefit
there so you could be a שומר חינם. Shomer Chinam. And the
last answer the גמרא is אי בעית אימא I ba'it eima what?
He's got his car.
Well that's true, but what what does the fact that I got
your car, what does it do for me? It doesn't give me
leverage. Leverage to do what?
Not return it!
But in order to extract get what to get what from the
guy? Meaning here there's a reality that you need to get paid
and you have the thing that's going to help you get paid,
right? The fact that I have this guy's car what does it
do for me? That I could steal it? I mean that's not
a benefit, right? Okay, אי בעית אימא I ba'it eima and if
you want you could say look, you're right. A שוכר Socher is
like an אומן Uman and whatever's true about a שוכר Socher is
true about an אומן. Uman. But we don't know that our משנה
is not like רבי מאיר. Why? Because there's a debate how to
what who says what when it comes to a שוכר. Socher. תניא
איפכא רבה בר בר חנה, Tanya ipcha Rabba bar bar Chana, רבה
בר בר חנה Rabba bar bar Chana reverses it. ותני שוכר כיצד
משלם רבי מאיר אומר כשומר שכר רבי יהודה אומר כשומר חינם. Vetani
socher keitzad meshallem Rabbi Meir omer keshomer sachar Rabbi Yehuda omer keshomer
chinam. He reverses it. So is our משנה רבי מאיר, רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, we don't know, because nobody knows what they hold about
a שוכר. Socher. But the other more interesting question is why should
a שוכר Socher be a שומר שכר Shomer Sachar and why should
an אומן? Uman? And the גמרא gave interesting reasons, at least one
in the end that it concludes with, which is that you can
use it as a leverage. That's a type of a benefit that
should make you into a שומר שכר. Shomer Sachar. That seems to
be the one the גמרא settles on. Okay.